Guide to the Clare Leighton Papers, 1940-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Clare Leighton papers 1940-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Leighton, Clare, 1898-1989
3.0 linear feet Extent: 500 Items
Clare Ellaline Hope Leighton was an English printmaker who immigrated to the United States in 1939. The Clare Leighton Papers date from the mid-twentieth century and include woodblocks, preparatory prints and drawings, and correspondence related to Leighton's artistic practice.
RL.00803
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Clare Leighton Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift.
Biographical Note
Clare Leighton was born in England in 1898. She studied at Brighton College of Art and the Central and Slade Schools in London. Leighton is best known for her books of stories and illustrations of agrarian subjects and the American South. The artist was a member of Duke University's Department of Art, Aesthetics, and Music from 1943 to 1945 and was awarded several prizes for her artistic achievements.
For more information, see Hickman, Caroline. "Clare Leighton and the American South." Duke Library Magazine Vol. 17, No. 3 (Spring/Summer 2004).
Collection Overview
The Clare Leighton Papers document Leighton's artistic production, and particularly her illustrations for the book Southern Harvest, published by the Macmillan Company in 1942, and The Frank C. Brown Collection of North Carolina Folklore, a seven-volume series published by Duke University Press from 1952-1964.
Materials in the collection include printer's proofs, preparatory sketches and prints, sketches, and a limited amount of correspondence related to the publication of Southern Harvest and to the acquisition of the Clare Leighton Papers.
Subject Headings
Leighton, Clare, 1898-1989; Wood-engraving -- 20th century; Illustrated books -- History -- 20th century; Duke University -- Faculty
Contents of Collection
- Woodblocks, 1940-1968, (1 box)
  The Woodblocks series contains a number of Leighton's blocks used for her wood engravings.
  - Wood Engraving Blocks (Box 1)
    Corn Husking, Baptizing, Fishing in Creek, Tobacco Barons, Sorghum, Coon Hunt, All Day Singing, Quilting Party, Herb Gatherers, Washing Clothes, Cockfight, Weeding Tobacco Bed, Dante Bookplate, Still, Wreck (block broken), Village Lovers, Windblown Tree, Cotton Picking, Centenarian, Chopping Cotton, Cotton Pickers, Spring House, Catfish, Cypress Swamp, and Mountain Girl
- Preparatory Materials, 1940-1968, (2 boxes)
  This series contains preparatory sketches and various sizes of prints. Some of these materials were used in the preparation of Leighton's book, Summer Harvest, and for her illustrations in the volumes of The Frank C. Brown Collection of North Carolina Folklore and Henry David Thoreau.
  - Bird Designs, Mural Polaroids (2), Assorted Small Prints, Bookplate Exhibition Materials (1967) (Box 2)
  - Preparatory Prints and Drawings for North Carolina Folklore (Box 2)
  - Preparatory Prints and Drawings for Southern Harvest (Box 2)
  - Printer's Proofs for Southern Harvest (Box 2)
  - Untitled Field Scene (Slide, Photo, and Negative) and Studies for Corn Shucking and Southern Harvest (1942) (Box 3)
  - A House Near Durham (Print and Accompanying Text) (Box 3)
  - Preparatory Prints, Drawing, and Proofs for illustrations of editions of Henry David Thoreau's Walden, Cape Cod, and The Maine Woods (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1940-1968, (1 folder)
  The Correspondence series includes limited documentation of Leighton's publication of Summer Harvest, as well as some materials related to the acquisition of the Clare Leighton Papers and art objects by the Rubenstein Library.
  - Leighton Correspondence and Acquisition Documentation (Box 2)
- Other Works, (1 box)
  This series contains materials relating to Clare Leighton's other artistic works.
  - Photographs of East Duke Building mural (Box 4)